hi my name is Joe Brewer and I'm a
change strategist today what I want to
do is talk with you about how economic
paradigms work and in particular how
large structural changes can happen in
economic systems on the global skate
stage and the book that I want to review
to help us understand them do this is
this really phenomenal piece of
scholarship technological revolutions
and financial capital the dynamics of
bubbles and golden ages by Carlota Perez
now this book what it does is it takes
you through the different stages of
economic paradigms by looking at the
changes in economic systems as if they
were complex adaptive systems said
another way when there is a convergence
of innovative new breakthrough ways of
doing technological development or
running a business some kind of an
innovation there is a process by which
financial capital is attracted to this
new wave of doing things that grows and
formalizes and crystallizes into an
interconnected web of communications
infrastructure production or
manufacturing infrastructure and
logistics or distribution infrastructure
and as this process goes along goes
through several distinct stages now what
collado Perez does in this book that is
extremely useful for us in the present
situation in the early 21st century as
she describes how boom-bust cycles arise
within financial systems and now these
boom-bust cycles are related to changes
in economic paradigms now we've just
gone through a boom-bust cycle with the
boom being the speculative bubble
starting in roughly 1980 and growing up
until late 2008-2009 when there was a
crash in the bubble and part of the
bubble disappeared that's what we call
the great financial crisis of 2009 or
the Great Recession and since that time
there has been a vast and yet subtle
shift in the organization of our
economic system moving away from a
production paradigm that is linear
centralized and built around very large
corporate and governmental
and moving into a world of distributed
collaborative open source Commons based
operations and entities using the
internet and using the various digital
infrastructure of smartphones and
distributed networks of communication
production and distribution so for us to
understand how this change process works
we really need to know what are the
underlying drivers that shape the
emerging patterns of economic systems
how these patterns can become stable and
robust and grow and accumulate to become
the dominant or primary way of doing
things in the world and then how that
dominant and primary way of doing things
can edify become rigid difficult to
change slow to adapt and then in a
disruptive environment like what we find
ourselves in today the entire thing can
begin a process of decay and collapse
and then there will be the rise of
another organized structured or self
organized and structured economic
paradigm so in the midst of this process
right now as we try to make the
transition to global sustainability and
move away from late modern era
capitalism and move into a
post-industrial period of production we
need to understand how these large-scale
economic patterns work and that's what
Carlota Perez does in this book
technological revolutions in financial
capital enjoy